<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An old apostate justly exposed his treachery to the Holy God, his truth and people manifested, his great wickedness and uncleanness (which, by false covers, he has endeavoured to hide) laid open to the shame of him, and all his abettors : in a short answer, or some brief remarks, upon a very scandalous book lately published, stiled, The spirit of Quakerism, and the danger of their divine revelation laid open, subscribed, Henry Winder : also the nameless publisher therof, as justly reprehended for his enmity and great malice, in abusing an innocent people, by heaps of most gross lies, slanders, base insinuations and inferences, frothy and scurrilous scoffs and taunts, so void of Christianity, that probably no man, with a name, would undertake / by Thomas Camm.</title>
            <author>Camm, Thomas, 1641-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12121900</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12121900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54462</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32898)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 591:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An old apostate justly exposed his treachery to the Holy God, his truth and people manifested, his great wickedness and uncleanness (which, by false covers, he has endeavoured to hide) laid open to the shame of him, and all his abettors : in a short answer, or some brief remarks, upon a very scandalous book lately published, stiled, The spirit of Quakerism, and the danger of their divine revelation laid open, subscribed, Henry Winder : also the nameless publisher therof, as justly reprehended for his enmity and great malice, in abusing an innocent people, by heaps of most gross lies, slanders, base insinuations and inferences, frothy and scurrilous scoffs and taunts, so void of Christianity, that probably no man, with a name, would undertake / by Thomas Camm.</title>
                  <author>Camm, Thomas, 1641-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Winder, Henry. --  Spirit of Quakerism and the danger of their divine revelation.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54462:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54462:1"/>
            <p>AN <hi>Old APOSTATE</hi> Juſtly Expoſed, His Treachery to the Holy <hi>God,</hi> his Truth and People MANIFESTED;</p>
            <p>His great Wickedneſs and Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (which, by Falſe Covers, he has Endeavoured to hide) laid open, to the Shame of him, and all his Abettors.</p>
            <p>In a ſhort Anſwer, or ſome Brief Remarks, upon a very Scandalous Book lately Publiſhed, Stiled, <hi>The Spirit of Quakeriſm, and the Danger of their Divine Revelation laid open;</hi> Subſcribed, <hi>Henry Winder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO The Nameleſs Publiſher thereof, as juſtly Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended for his Enmity and great Malice, in Abuſing an Innocent People, by heaps of moſt Groſs Lies, Slanders, Baſe Inſinuations and Inferences, Frothy and Scurrilous Scoffs and Taunts; ſo void of Chriſtianity, that probably no Man, with a Name, would Undertake.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS CAMM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> next Door to the <hi>Meeting-houſe</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet.</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet,</hi> near the <hi>Market,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:54462:2"/>
            <q>The Dog is turned to his own vomit again, and the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the Mire,
<bibl>
                  <hi>2. Pet. 2.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>They went out from us, but they were not of us, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                  <hi>John 2.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Raging Waves of the Sea, foaming out their own Shame, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Jude 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Behold he Travelleth with Iniquity, and hath conceived Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and brought forth Falſhood; he made a Pit and digged it, and is fallen into the Ditch which he made: his Miſchief ſhall return upon his own Head, and his Violent Dealing ſhall come down upon his own Pate,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 7.14, 15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54462:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE. TO THE Impartial Reader.</head>
            <p>IF thou haſt Seen or Read a Book lately Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, Stiled, <hi>The Spirit of Quakeriſm, and the Danger of their Divine Revelation laid open,</hi> Subſcribed, <hi>Hen. Winder,</hi> then be pleaſed to ſuſpend giving Judgment upon the Matter thereof, until thou haſt Read, and duly Conſidered the Contents of what follows; being a ſhort Anſwer, or ſome brief Remarks upon the moſt material Paſſages in that <hi>Book,</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled againſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> and thoſe People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember what the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>viz. He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth Juſt, but his Neighbour cometh and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him.</hi> If thou judge that I have been cloſe upon the Author, and have expoſed him to publick view, conſider that he has been the
<pb facs="tcp:54462:3"/>occaſion: And what is written in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be fulfilled, <hi>viz. The Wickedneſs of the Wicked muſt return upon his own Head; and he that hides his Sins cannot Proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs I was Aſtoniſhed to ſee the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber before named grown ſo Impudent Hard, ſince I had ſome ſmall knowledge of him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years paſt, while he ſeemed to be of us, and before he fell into ſuch groſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs: And have ſeen, yea, having by me ſeveral of his Confeſſions and Acknowledgments, not only of his great Sins and Tranſgreſſions, but alſo to the Truth and Way thereof, and that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the People that walk therein: I ſay, I was Aſtoniſhed to ſee the Man now grown ſo Seared, as to give himſelf the Lie, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Print againſt the <hi>Truth</hi> and Innocent <hi>People</hi> thereof, with that Inconſiderateneſs and Fury, which manifeſts him to be one of them Evil Men, who grows worſe and worſe; and to have entertained again that Evil Spirit (that was in ſome meaſure once caſt out) and with him ſeven times worſe, which makes his latter end much worſe than his beginning. I ſhall not take notice of all his long <hi>Narrative,</hi> but ſuch as chiefly Reflects upon the <hi>Truth,</hi> and People of God called <hi>Quakers:</hi> My Intent and Aim be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeceive or Inform them who have
<pb facs="tcp:54462:3"/>believed his Falſe Reports, and Deceitful Slanderous Inſinuations againſt the Truth and Principle thereof, which we Profeſs: As alſo to Detect his falſe Pretences in his going from Truth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and deſerting that Profeſſion that once he made thereof with us, by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating the True Cauſe thereof; neither ſhall I Juſtifie the Three Women in any thing wherein they miſſed the Line of Truth; which, to his Conſcience is known, we never owned them in; though he would now (being filled with Enmity) Falſly Inſinuate we did, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Prejudice the Minds of People, againſt that Way of Truth from which he is now fallen, through Sin and Wickedneſs: And for a Cover thereto; as alſo to gratifie ſuch amongſt them with whom he is now joyned, as Luſts to be Envious, and whoſe Fingers Itches to be at their old Work of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being angry at the Liberty we now (through God's Great Mercy) enjoy, as to our Religious Duties, from the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for which we deſire ever to be Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all Grateful Acknowledgments. How aptly what follows doth anſwer to what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore propoſed, I leave to thee, Impartial Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to Judge; Recommending thee to the Guidance of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nerring Spirit, that gives a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and Leads into all
<pb facs="tcp:54462:4"/>Truth. And that thou and all Men might come under the Guidance and Government thereof, is the Earneſt Deſire of him, who wiſheth Good to all Men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Camm.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54462:4"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Old Apoſtate</hi> Juſtly Expoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Hen. Winder.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WILL not thy own Back-ſliding Correct thee, and is it not a Dreadful Thing, that thou ſhould ſo far harden thy Heart againſt God, and the Convictions of his Spirit in thy own Conſcience, for thy great and manifold Sins, ſo as to grow, as Evil Men always do, worſe and worſe; making Shipwrack of Faith and a Good Conſcience; being Seared as with an Hot Iron, to the fulfilling the Teſtimony of Holy Scripture upon thee, <hi>viz. Becauſe Judgment from God has not been ſpeedily Executed, thy heart has been more ſet to do Evil?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thy Book, if it be thine, as by thee Subſcribed, and as I hear in part owned to be ſo; I have ſeen, read and conſidered of, and find thy Enmity great, and thy ſaid Book, chiefly bent againſt the Truth, and People called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Innocent People to the Fury and Scorn of Malicious Men, ſuch as the nameleſs Publiſher thereof: For if thou had bent thy ſelf only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe thou names as Injurers of thee, ſince
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54462:5"/>they miſſed in their Management, in that they Charge thee with; whether all true or not, we leave to him who knows all things, and is the Searcher of all Hearts; yet I ſhould not have concerned my ſelf on this wiſe, but finding that through their Sides, thou endeavoureſt to ſtrike at Truth (againſt which thou cannot prevail) and the Principle thereof born Teſtimony unto, by thoſe Innocent People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to take notice of thy Book, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, thy Title is, <hi>The Spirit of Quakeriſm;</hi> An old Nickname, more beſeeming one that had never born the name of a <hi>Quaker,</hi> than thee that once did; and to what follows, <hi>viz.</hi> The danger of their Divine Revelation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Divine Revelation the <hi>Quakers</hi> own, it's Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Doctrine, without it none can come to the True and Saving Knowledge of the Only True God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, <hi>whom to know is Life Eternal:</hi> For it's the Teſtimony of Holy Scripture, <hi>That no Man knows the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals him.</hi> And this Revelation is the Divine; and the very ſame Divine Revelation is what the <hi>Quakers</hi> own, and are not Aſhamed of; and is great wickedneſs in thee to count it Dangerous, or inconſiſtent with Scripture-Teſtimony. Thou calls thy Book, <hi>A Faithful Narrative of their</hi> (meaning the Quakers) <hi>Malicious Perſecution of</hi> H. W. <hi>and his Wife, as Murtherers, at the publick Aſſize at</hi> Carliſle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Narrative is neither Faithful nor True, but greatly Malicious, as it is given in ſo general Terms againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and in part
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54462:5"/>Aggravated as to the three Women, mentioned by name, as may more fully appear in what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
                  <p>Thou begins thy Preface thus, <hi>viz. Being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by Perſons of Worth and Eminency, to give a Publick Account,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>At laſt, I aſſented,</hi> ſay'ſt thou, <hi>to their Importunities,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Perſons of either Worth or Eminency (by what follows) I doubt not will have good cauſe to deteſt thy Abominable Wickedneſs, and conclude, thou haſt juſtly Expoſed thy ſelf, and all thy publick Abettors to great and publick Infamy.</p>
                  <p>Thou adds,
<q>The wrong they have done me, was a ſufficient Incentive to have bent all my Strength to have made all their Villainy as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious as poſſible; nevertheleſs they ſee, and the World ſees, how ſlow I have been to do it.</q> Then gives 1ſt, 2d, and 3d. Reaſons therefore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Quakers</hi> had done thee no wrong, and it's yet Queſtionable, whether the three Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (though wrong in their management againſt him, and might miſs in ſome Circumſtances) have wronged him in the main; it's known to God, and his own Conſcience, to whom I leave the Judgment thereof, deſiring the Readers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and to ſuſpend his Judging thereof, until he has Read, and Seriouſly Conſidered what the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> and Wife have given under their hands, with what elſe is herein after Inſerted, relating thereto; and the World has ſeen, and under his hand we have an Account of what he has done to the ſaid three Women, and their Husbands; and alſo may now ſee what he has
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54462:6"/>done to the <hi>Quakers;</hi> and if the Malice that may yet reſt in his, or the Hearts of his Abettors, can do more, let them do it quickly.</p>
                  <p>His Reaſons pretended for his Slowneſs are Idle, Impertinent and Fallacious: For will not Wiſe Men judge it more ſeaſonable to Detect Perſons for wrong, when Living and Capable either of Defence or making Satisfaction, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which the Dead can do; and his now Trampling upon their Graves is no good ſign of Innocency; but I ſhall only ask him, if there was not ſome other Reaſons: 1ſt, Was his Heart before now grown hard enough for ſuch a work? And 2dly, Whether he preſumed that length of time had not buried the Memory of his Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and made a prey of what he had written and ſaid, relating to the Demonſtration thereof? 3dly, Whether he was not too far prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſome of thoſe People amongſt whom he now walks, who are apt enough (I ſay, ſome Hot Heads amongſt them) I make that diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe I know there are Sober-minded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and, as I hear, are not pleaſed with his Book; and perhaps will find cauſe to be more diſpleaſed) to catch at any thing, tho' never ſo Dirty, if they can but throw it at the Deſpiſed People called <hi>Quakers?</hi> And doth not his ſaying, <hi>At laſt I aſſented to their Importunities;</hi> and that kind of Sorrowful or Lamenting Saying of his Wife, <hi>viz. Ah we were put upon it, or elſe we had never done it;</hi> greatly demonſtrate that they have now of late been too far prevailed upon, and perſuaded to what they have done, to the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of a Wrathful Spirit, in which work they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54462:6"/>will never be Bleſſed, but will undoubtedly meet with Shame?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall take notice of ſome Paſſages, of what I find given as his ſecond Reaſon for his Slowneſs, yet not becauſe it is either Reaſonable or Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to that matter, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <q>But afterward thought it a dignity far ſurpaſſing my deſerts, that God ſhould chuſe me his Inſtrument, to Fight this Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when I conſider (ſaith he) what Perſons our Saviour choſe for his Great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> O Impudent Man, would he be taken for God's choſen Inſtrument! no ſure, he muſt be a cleaner Man firſt, and our Bleſſed Saviour, Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> choſe neither <hi>Whoremongers</hi> not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers</hi> for his Great Apoſtles; no, their Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſtood in Holineſs, and <hi>Whoremongers</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers</hi> have no place in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> no, the God that choſe him (unclean Man) is the God of the World, who has ſuch Inſtruments, to Battel with the <hi>Lamb</hi> and his followers; and the dignity that he gets by this his Work, will appear by what follows.</p>
                  <p>I now come to his Narrative, paſſing by at preſent what the Publiſher adds to the Preface, Intending in its proper ſeaſon to take notice of what the Nameleſs Publiſher adds, there and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
                  <p>In Page the 2d. <hi>H. W.</hi> on behalf of Himſelf and Wife, ſaith,
<q>But being Conſcious of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Innocency, we made our appeal to the Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again in Page the 3d.
<q>We know no guilt, you are falſe Propheteſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54462:7"/>
                  <p> In Page the 11th.
<q>A Burthen Intolerable, had I not been ſupported by a God of Truth, and a clear Conſcience.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In Anſwer to all which, I offer what follows, taken out of their own Papers, <hi>viz. H. W.</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> and owned very late ſo to be by them, or the one of them, before ſeveral Witneſſes, whoſe Names are after Inſerted, which Papers are Dated from the Year 1674. about the time that our Friends had denied them, for their Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Wickedneſs; And Wrath and Judgment from the Lord being upon them, therefore they Writ, and gave under their Hands two Papers, as followeth:</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Oh! Dearly Beloved and Choſen of God, ye are the Children of the moſt High God, and Church of whom Chriſt is Head; Hear us we pray you, and we ſhall diſcover our Hearts to you, Firſt, we Acknowledge and Confeſs that we have Sinned and Tranſgreſſed againſt the Lord God, and againſt his People, who have born grievous Burthens for us, we muſt needs confeſs before you. But this know, Dear Friends, that the Enemy wrought in a Miſtery in us, to the perſuading of us that we might do ſuch things, and yet Live; then, through the weakneſs of the Fleſh, Sin took Occaſion and overcame us; then Sin being committed it brought forth Death to the Innocent Life, which we once Lived in; then the Lord hid his Preſence from us, which we once Injoyed, and left us to our ſelves; then we were as Sheep without a Shepherd, wandering upon the Barren Mountains, where there was no Food
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54462:7"/>for the Soul; ſo let us be a Warning to all Backſliders, and thoſe that turn from the Grace of God into any Unrighteouſneſs: For there will be a loſing of the Preſence of the Lord, and of the Incomes of his Love unto the Soul, which is the greateſt Loſs of all Loſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—For when Luſt was conceived in us it brought forth Sin, and when Sin was finiſhed, it brought forth Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — The Lord made known himſelf unto us, both by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Working in us, and by his Meſſenger unto us, <hi>Margaret Bradley,</hi> who is a Faithful Servant of God, and a Lover of our Souls, who hath Travelled in pain for us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— The Lord Reward her for her Faithfulneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord and us, as no doubt but he hath Rewarded her already: Ah! you Beloved of us, we do this Acknowledge and Confeſs, that we have been ſuch a grievous Burthen and Shame unto you, in giving ſo great Occaſion to the Enemy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beſides you were even pricked to the Heart for us: Now we are unworthy and alſo aſhamed to come into your Congregations, or into the Aſſembly of Friends, thoſe which we have ſo grievouſly Sinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—We intreat you, if you can find ſo much Favour and Love in your Hearts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, as to receive us into your Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, if it be but into the Entry of your Houſes, where you meet together to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> This out of one of their ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; now hear alſo what follows, taken out of the Second, beginning thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Be it known unto all People, unto whom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54462:8"/>theſe Preſents ſhall be read, That I <hi>H. Winder,</hi> and <hi>Ann</hi> my Wife, do acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs before the Living God, and unto all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, That we have Sinned, and done that which we ought not to have done, in ſuffering the Temptations of Sin in the Fleſh to overcome us, and lead us out of the ſtrait and narrow Way which leads to Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—So this know all People, that it was not becauſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> Judgment, or Doctrine, or way of Worſhip is Falſe, that it cauſed us to fall from them; But our fall was of our ſelves; and their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their Doctrine, their way of Worſhip and Faith is Acceptable with the Lord, we do Faithfully Believe it, and alſo Acknowledge it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—He hath called us to Repentance; <hi>For he would not the Death of a Sinner, but rather that he ſhould Repent and Live,</hi> &amp;c. — I was afraid, and hid my ſelf five days, but my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering was too narrow; but the Word of the Lord came to me again, ſaying, Hide not thy ſelf, nor be not Rebellious any longer: For I the Lord fill Heaven and Earth with my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; therefore confeſs thy Sins and Repent, and forſake them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Then I fell down at the Word of the Lord Trembling, Faſting and Praying, Weeping and Mourning before the Lord three days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Let all People take Warning by me, to call to Remembrance their former Sins and Tranſgreſſions, which they have committed before the Lord God, for he fills Heaven and Earth with his Preſence, and nothing can be hid from him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Let the Wicked forſake his Ways, and the Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54462:8"/>his Thoughts, and let us turn unto the Lord with penitent Hearts, confeſſing the Evil of our Doings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> Thus far out of the ſaid two Papers, faithfully taken out; which if any ſhall queſtion, I hereby profer ſuch, if they pleaſe, to read them at large. And let it be noted, Reader, that upon the 15th of the 1ſt Month, commonly called <hi>March</hi> laſt paſt, thoſe two Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, out of which I have taken what is above-written, was then intended to have been ſhewed to both <hi>H. W</hi> and his <hi>Wife,</hi> but he not being met with, the ſaid <hi>Ann</hi> his Wife did then own them to be their own Papers, and that ſhe Writ them with her own Hands. And did alſo then own the Preface, Narrative and Poſtſcript of that Book, called, <hi>The Spirit of Quakeriſm,</hi> &amp;c. to be her Husband's. And being further queried, why they ſhould put forth ſuch a Wicked Book, ſhe anſwered, <hi>Ah! we were put upon it by ſeveral, elſe we had never done it;</hi> but would not tell who they were, though then deſired, only confeſſed that Mr. <hi>Gillpin</hi> wrote down all things thereof, as they were Tranſacted. And the ſaid <hi>Ann, H. W</hi>'s Wife, querying then of our Friends, whoſe Names are after Subſcribed as Witneſſes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we intended to anſwer their ſaid Book; our Friends anſwering, Yea, it would be Anſwered; to which ſhe replyed, <hi>And then will you lay us open to the World,</hi> &amp;c. Witneſſes hereof</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Grenhope.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Greenhow.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Bowſtead.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Atkinſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I ſhall now add what is ſo Notoriouſly known in the face of the Neighbourhood, that though
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54462:9"/>the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> be greatly hardned, yet I preſume he cannot have a face to deny; relating to their great uncleanneſs, for which they were denyed of us <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> had her that is now his Wife, ſo great with Child in his firſt Wife's dayes, that there was but about ſix Weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Death of his firſt Wife, and the Birth of that Child.</p>
            <p>Now Reader be pleaſed to compare what is before taken out of their own Papers, and what is added as a demonſtration of their great Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and Uncleanneſs, that their Papers have relation to (and for which they were denyed of our Friends) with what I have in ſhort before cited out of their own Book, <hi>viz.</hi> that God ſhould chooſe him, <hi>viz. H. W.</hi> to be his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to Fight this Battle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <q>And when I conſider, what Perſons our Saviour choſe for his great Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But being Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of our perfect Innocency, we made our Appeal to the Searcher of all Hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we know no Guilt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again, a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Intolerable, had I not been Supported by a God of Truth, and a clear Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And then Reader, after ſuch comparing the One with the Other, and due Conſideration thereof, I ſhall leave it to thee, if thou be ſuch an one as hath the Fear of God before thee, to judge, whether this our Adverſary <hi>H. W.</hi> is like an Inſtrument choſen of the Pure Holy God, or in any reſpect like the Apoſtles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jeſus,</hi> fit to be dignified by appearing on God's behalf: Can be Conſcious of perfect In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54462:9"/>or can as ſuch, make his appeal to the Searcher of all Hearts, can know no guilt: Can be ſupported by a God of Truth, and a clear Conſcience, or no: And whether it be not great Impiety and Blaſphemous in him ſo to ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his Circumſtances as before? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it doth not beſpeak and declare his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be Seared, as with an Hot Iron, or no? Ah ſurely the Righteous God will Rebuke him for his Abominable Uncleanneſs and Impiety, Hypocriſie, and make him, and all his Abettors, Examples in his Wrath, If they Repent not.</p>
            <p>Further, let the Reader obſerve, that the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> in the firſt Page of his Narrative, ſaith, That it was in the Year 1673. and Harveſt time, when <hi>Margaret Bradley,</hi> one of the three Women, he calls his Accuſers, came with a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to him, and after the Relation of her then Meſſage to him, he alſo relates his Anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> 'The Lord Rebuke thee, thou Impudent Wretch. And in Page 2. he ſaith,
<q>That not long after came <hi>M. L.</hi> with the ſame Meſſage.</q> And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame Page, he ſaith,
<q>We oppoſed them, to Convince, if poſſible, by all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments we could uſe, that their pretended Revelations came from the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </q> And in Page 3. Calls them, Poor Deluded Creatures, Falſe Propheteſſes, and that he thought the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> had led them ſo far, that he could not bring them off, without Confuſion and Shame.</p>
            <p>Now, Reader, I ſay again, be pleaſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare what I have above Cited out of the three firſt Pages of his Narrative, with what I have before taken out of their two Papers, relating
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54462:10"/>to <hi>Margaret Bradley,</hi> and then conſider when, and in what time, we ſhall believe <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife, whether in what they ſay in their Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, in the Pages aforeſaid, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend was ſpoken in the Year 1673. or in their Papers written in 1674. the Year next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſince they ſo poſitively Contradict each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For in the firſt Year 1673. She, the ſaid <hi>M. B.</hi> is an Impudent Wretch, that her Meſſage or Revelation came from the Devil; a Deluded Creature, a Falſe Propheteſs, one that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil had in <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife's Thoughts led ſo far, that he could not bring her back without Shame and Confuſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in their Paper under their Hands, and owned, as before ſaid, written in the Year 1674. next following, fully contradicts what they would now ſay or pretend was ſpoken in the Year before; for in this later Year, ſhe, <hi>viz. Margaret Bradley,</hi> is God's Meſſenger to them, a Faithful Servant of God, a Lover of their Souls, one who Travelled in Pain for them; deſires that the Lord may Reward her for her Faithfulneſs between the Lord and them: And concludes with, that no doubt but the Lord hath already Rewarded her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Conſiderate Reader, which of the two is to be believed as true, firſt or laſt (or both) which cannot be, being ſo abſolutely Contrary; except they grant, they wronged her in the firſt, and that ſhe was ſtill what in the latter they ſay; if they had rightly underſtood her, and her Meſſage; and if the firſt be true, and that ſhe was worthy of ſuch Vile Terms in 1673. then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54462:10"/>how comes ſhe to deſerve ſuch an Honourable Character in 1674. was not her Meſſage ſtill the ſame, if they alledge ſhe was become a better, yea, a good Woman, will that do? no, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the the Contradiction before, the Meſſage being ſtill the ſame; and if the laſt be true, and to be Believed, as by them Subſcribed to, and ſince owned, as before ſaid, written in 1674. then how will <hi>H. W.</hi> juſtifie his Proſecution of her at Law upon the Score of the ſaid Meſſage. But I obſerve the Serpents Way is very Crooked, full of Deceitful Doubles, and he Deceives all at laſt, who follow him, by leading them where they cannot return without Shame and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; where the Reader may ſee he hath led <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife; the old Proverb is, <hi>Liers ought to have a good Memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may it not be reaſonably concluded, by what is before ſaid, that it was the real Senſe of <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife, when their Papers were written; they being then under the Sence of the Righteous Judgments of God, for their great Sins, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Year 1674. before they had hardened their Hearts againſt the Lord; and that what is pretended to be ſpoken in the Year 1673. is but only Stuff, through Enmity and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice ſince entered into their Hearts, againſt the Truth and God's People; and now Introduced to Amuſe and Deceive the Unwary Reader, and with more colour to reflect upon, and aſperſe an Innocent People, as alſo to hide and cover their great Wickedneſs. And in as much as they are Witneſſes under their own Hands, That ſhe, <hi>viz. M. B.</hi> was a Servant of God, and his Meſſenger
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54462:11"/>to them in 74. What notice is to be taken, or credit to be given, to what in the Year before, is now pretended to be ſpoken upon her ſaid Meſſage, but to be exploded and looked upon as the product of great Enmity againſt the Truth, and People from which he is fallen; and to Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his Aſſiſtants and Abettors, ſuch as his Wife ſaith, urged or put them upon Writing and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing in Print, elſe they had never done it; who, together with them, will juſtly, for their pains, reap Infamy and Shame; <hi>For the Wickedneſs of the Wicked will return upon his own Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſhe was a Faithful Servant of the Lord, and his Meſſenger to them, as they ſay, under their Hands, in their ſaid Papers; I ask <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife, what was the Meſſage ſhe brought them? Was it what they have Inſerted in their ſaid Book, which ſhe Charged them with? Then I further query of them, how they will evade the matter of Fact Charged againſt them therein, or excuſe themſelves from the Guilt thereof, ſince they ſay, <hi>She was to them God's Meſſenger,</hi> &amp;c. For I find no other Meſſage or Charge Inſerted in the ſaid Book, Charged againſt the ſaid <hi>M. B.</hi> and other two Women, except what he mentions in Page 11. viz. <hi>They</hi> (meaning the three Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or ſome of them) <hi>had new Revelations,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>That I was guilty of the Death of ſome Perſon, nearly Related to them and me.</hi> But who this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was, or how Related, either to them or him, he mentions not, but leaves his Reader in the Dark.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I now Query, if it was his firſt Wife he means; for ſure ſhe was, or at leaſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54462:11"/>ought to have been nearly Related to him; but ſuch Diſhoneſt and Unfaithful Men to their Wives as he who loudly Luſts after others, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Love, or be ſo nearly Related to their own Wives as they ought to be; and if it be his firſt Wife he means, and yet Conceals her, it might be Policy; I will not ſay Wiſdom, except De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh; leſt the nameing her might revive that Jealouſie of wrong to her, upon her ſudden and unexpected Death; and the Circumſtances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Related, That ſhe that was his then— and his now Wife was then under. O how Groſs things looks; And it's Irkſome to me to meddle in ſuch Dirty Stuff, if it were not to wipe it off the Innocent, and caſt it back where it ought to ſtick; wherefore I ſhall take notice of another great Circumſtance of more Wickedneſs than was clearly Diſcovered.</p>
            <p>That is, that when the Siſters, and near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of her that is now Wife to <hi>H. W.</hi> was Jealous of her being with Child, about the time of the Death of <hi>H. W</hi>'s firſt Wife, and ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being queſtioned, yet ſtoutly denied; they for better Satisfaction did ſearch her; and found Milk in her Breaſts, which I ſuppoſe is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken amongſt Women for an undoubted To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of being with Child, except ſuch as give Suck. And their preſſing that as a Certain To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of her being ſo, yet ſhe, to blind them, and to hide, if ſhe could, her Condition, replied to them then on this wiſe, <hi>viz. I have been ſo once before, and you never knew any thing but well with me.</hi> This ſhe confeſſed ſhe then ſpake, before the four Friends before named, the 15th of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54462:12"/>firſt Month laſt paſt, only with this throw at her Relations, <hi>But my Relations has been my great Enemies in the matter.</hi>—Now if ſhe had been ſo once before; that is, had Milk in her Breaſts: Which is, as I ſuppoſe, a common Token of being with Child; and if ſhe was before with Child, it muſt be either by <hi>H. W.</hi> or ſome other Man; I ſhall only ask, if ſo, what became of that Child? And ſhall leave both the further Search and Judgment thereof to him who knows all things, and cannot be deceived.</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall take notice of, is what he ſaith in his Poſtſcript, if it be his, however his Name is to it, whoever was the Author, which Intitles him to it, though moſt Falſe in the greateſt part thereof, as after may more fully appear, by what follows.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Page of the ſaid Poſtſcript, and 19th of his Book, he ſaith,
<q>That ſome, after my entrance amongſt them (meaning the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>) they repoſed a great truſt in me, <hi>viz.</hi> to be Receiver of all their Collections in the County, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Had not <hi>Judas,</hi> the Betrayer of our Bleſſed Lord, as great a Truſt, or greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in him; for he was not only the keeper or bearer of the Bag, for the neceſſity of the Poor, <hi>&amp;t.</hi> but was Intruſted in a part of the Miniſtry; yet notwithſtanding Wickedly Betrayed his Lord and Maſter, going to the High Prieſts to make his Bargain with them; and has not <hi>H. W.</hi> Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated him, in endeavouring (with the aſſiſtance of ſome, at leaſt like the High Prieſts) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Innocent into the Hands of the Wicked?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54462:12"/>Wherefore let <hi>H. W.</hi> conſider the Diſmal End of <hi>Judas,</hi> and take heed leſt his be the like.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of the ſaid Poſtſcript is made up of baſe Reflections againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as that they were changed from what they were, and become Erroneous in both Doctrine and Practice, that there was much Jarring, Diſcord, Secret Envying, and Different Opinions among them; then moſt Falſly and Wickedly Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that thereby he found much Diſquietneſs and Anguiſh in his Mind, which put him upon a new Examination of the Grounds of Religion, and being better Informed, could not with clear Conſcience ſtay amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, which ſo offended the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that ever after they made him their Butt to Shoot at, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That what is before pretended, is Wickedly Falſe, will moſt evidently appear in what follows: For that they fell from us through great Uncleanneſs, is before Demonſtrated, and we have their Confeſſion thereof, under their own Hands, as before taken out of their Papers, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Be it known unto all People, unto whom theſe Preſents ſhall be read, That I <hi>H. Winder</hi> and my Wife, do Acknowledge and Confeſs before the Living God, and unto all People, That we have Sinned, and done that which we ought not to have done, in ſuffering the Temptations of Sin in the Fleſh to overcome us, and lead us out of the ſtrait and narrow way which leads to Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So this know all People (let the Reader Mark) that it was not becauſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> Judgment, or Doctrine,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54462:13"/>or way of Worſhip is Falſe, that it cauſed us to fall from them, but our fall was of our ſelves: And their Judgment, their Doctrine, their way of Worſhip and Faith is acceptable to the Lord, we do Faithfully Believe it, and alſo Acknowledge it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us be a Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto all Backſliders, and thoſe that turn from the Grace of God into any Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now can any thing be more Clear and Plain, than that what <hi>H. W.</hi> pretends, in his ſaid Poſtſcript, to be the Reaſons of a New Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Grounds of Religion, and his leaving them is moſt Horrid and Wickedly Falſe; a very Helliſh Device to Beſpatter the Truth and Profeſſers thereof, to gratifie the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed Enemies thereof, to Deceive and Beguile his Unwary Reader, and to his hide great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, by which he Fell. Oh Falſe and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hardened Man! The Lord ſees his Deceit and Abominable Wickedneſs, and will Reward accordingly, except ſpeedy Repentance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <p>Is it not a Dreadful thing to ſee Men ſo, to make Shipwrack of Faith and good Conſcience, as <hi>H. W.</hi> has done in ſo poſitive a Contradiction of what in the Year 74. when the Hand of the Lord was upon him for his Sins in Judgment, he ſo Faithfully and in ſo Solemn Words, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared as in the preſence of the Living God, was the Cauſe of their falling from the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as aforeſaid. So that <hi>H. W.</hi> has Contradicted the Falſe Charges of <hi>H. W.</hi> againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Hand, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are ſtill what
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54462:13"/>they were, not changed, in Unity and Concord; of one Heart and Spirit, their Judgment and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Faith and way of Worſhip acceptable to God: And the ground of the Sorrow and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh he tells of, are his Sins; under which Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it had been well for him if he had kept, if it was Godly, till it had wrought true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Who would then have had no need of ſuch ſordid Shifts and deceitful Covers? But, alas! the <hi>Quakers</hi> way was too ſtrait for him, the <hi>Quakers</hi> Judgment too cloſe upon him for his notorious vileneſs, their Religion ſuch as would not admit of his abominable uncleanneſs: So fleſhly minded Man muſt have a broader way, where ſome ſoft Pillows muſt be put under to lean upon a Religion, in which there's more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Fleſh, and yet be counted a Saint, one of the very Elect; ſo from the <hi>Quakers</hi> to them he went; and let him conſider <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.24, 25. And if they be better for him, or have got Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by receiving of him, they may hold him; for the <hi>Quakers</hi> can well ſpare him, till he be a cleaner Man, and hates Lying, and every evil Way.</p>
            <p>The next Remark is, his Endeavours to faſten what he calls the Tragedy, upon the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general; or, at leaſt, upon a great Party of them: As in Page 6. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Now theſe Women, (meaning his now Wifes two Siſters, and <hi>M. B.</hi> before named) mightily beſtirred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and had quickly got a great Party of Friends inclining to their Opinion, ſo far as to declare them true Propheteſſes, as <hi>J. S.</hi> of <hi>How,</hi> a great Speaker in Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54462:14"/>in Page 12. That many other <hi>Quakers,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially their Husbands, were intoxicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in Page 18. With the Aſſiſtance of, and Approbation of many other <hi>Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. And in Page 21. This did much diſpleaſe the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> &amp;c. Again, in Page 22. They (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Quakers</hi>) began to envy me, and their Love was turned into Malice, which eats like a Canker; from which at laſt broke out the aforeſaid Tragedy. If this was not the thing that ſo incenſed them againſt me, I know not what was, except what I ſaid before of <hi>Mary Dawſon.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I obſerve how high and ſtrange he chargeth, but very low and feeble in Proof; the great Party of Friends ends only in <hi>J. S.</hi> with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> one who is many Years ſince in his Grave; as is all or moſt elſe whom he dares to charge by Name on any account in his ſaid Book, who are no ways capable of making Defence, though never ſo much wronged and abuſed. And his many other <hi>Quakers</hi> Ends, with, <hi>eſpecially their Husbands,</hi> meaning the three Women, and for the many <hi>Quakers</hi> that approved the ſaid Women, and whoſe Love turned into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and cankered Malice; From whence, he would moſt falſly inſinuate, ſprung the ſaid Tragedy, and that he was made the <hi>Quakers</hi> Mark to ſhoot at; he names not one: So that it's evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he fails, and comes off very meanly, in proving that either the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general, or a great part of them, or any part of them, was any ways concerned in what he endeavours through Malice to faſten upon them. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54462:14"/>though the <hi>Quakers</hi> and others may ſuppoſe him guilty of many vile and groſs things, and by him under his own Hand acknowledged and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; yet, notwithſtanding, never owned the ſaid three Women in their Complaints to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, in order to proſecute him at Law; but I and all other of our Friends, ſo far as I know or have heard, diſowned them therein from the very firſt of their appearance therein; and I challenge <hi>H. W.</hi> to name any one of our Friends living, if he can, of whom he can prove the contrary: Beſides, we can make appear, under the Hands of ſome of thoſe three, in the time of their Impriſonment, that we had diſowned them in their Proceedings aforeſaid, they then complaining how it added to their then Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, becauſe we then could not own them therein. So that it's evident, it's cankered Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in <hi>H. W.</hi> to charge the <hi>Quakers</hi> in being concerned in the ſaid Endeavours of Proſecution at Law; knowing, that though he may prove never ſo guilty of what the three Women charges againſt him, yet they miſled the way of Truth in their Complaints and endeavours of Proſecution aforeſaid, for what, as notoriouſly appeared, ought to have been by them left to the Cenſure of that Church or Community he had ſome time walked amongſt, and made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to be of, and the reſt to him to whom Secrets belongs, who knoweth things, and will judge Righteouſly. And it hath been, and is my preſent Senſe, That the wicked One who had led this <hi>H. W.</hi> into ſuch groſs Evils, did by the occaſion of their endeavouring Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54462:15"/>in the way aforeſaid, harden his Heart, to turn againſt them, as much as in him lay, to rend and tear them in Revenge; and not only ſo, but to calumniate and aſperſe the Truth, and thoſe that walk in it: For it's obſervable, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their endeavours of Proſecution, in that way aforeſaid, not only thoſe three Women, but ſeveral other of our Friends, found him more ſoft and tender, making ſuch Acknowledgments and Confeſſions, as before inſerted, and ſome more, which, for good Reaſons, I ſhall not now publiſh, nor incline thereto, if <hi>H. W.</hi> miniſter not juſt occaſion therefore, as before ſaid. And in as much as theſe three Perſons miſſed the way of Truth in their Endeavours of Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the way aforeſaid, and was diſowned by all our Friends that I know of, Then how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt is <hi>H. W.</hi> notwithſtanding, to charge us with what we are ſo innocent and clear of? Which declares him the Perſon guilty of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that eats like a Canker.</p>
            <p>Now, I hope, the honeſt and unprejudiced Reader will be fully and clearly ſatisfied by what's before ſaid, that what <hi>H. W.</hi> pretends to be the Reaſons of his deſerting us, are falſe and feigned; and that he is very unjuſt, in charging the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the endeavours of Proſecution aforeſaid, and that the Envy of the <hi>Quakers</hi> was the ground thereof; the contrary being made appear. Neither can I in Charity conclude, That either Envy or Malice in the ſaid three Perſons, was the ground of their ſo endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proſecution as aforeſaid; but, rather, an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54462:15"/>hot Indignation and ungoverned Zeal, againſt his abominable and groſs Uncleanneſs.</p>
            <p>I now come to examine what he concludes in his ſaid Poſtſcript, before hinted, <hi>viz.</hi> If it was not the Envy and Malice of the <hi>Quakers</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting; That was the ground of what he calls the Tragedy, he knows not what was, except he what ſaid before of <hi>M. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Man is hard beſet, put to all his ſhifts, yet when he ſhould conclude, knows not where, nor upon what: So uncertain is he, That it muſt be either this or that, elſe he knows not what: And though it be neither this, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> Envy and Malice, nor that relating to <hi>M. D.</hi> I ſhall tell him the true Cauſe thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, his vile Uncleanneſs: Secondly, an hot In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, an ungoverned Zeal in the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſaid, againſt that his ſhameful and vile Uncleanneſs: And the <hi>Quakers</hi> clear of both.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, I ſhall for the Information of the Reader, and clearing Truth, as alſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the poor ſorry fallacious ſhifts of this Man, to his ſhame and confuſion; I ſay I ſhall, for the Reaſons aforeſaid, examine what relates to <hi>M. D.</hi> as I find it in the 13th and 14th Pages of his ſaid Book, under a Note, as ſome remarkable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; which take as followeth, <hi>viz. Note,</hi> That this <hi>Mary Langhorne,</hi> was formerly the Wife of <hi>John Dawſon</hi> of <hi>Hutton-John;</hi> after whoſe Death ſhe did at divers times expreſs to <hi>H. W.</hi> (then a Widower) her great affection and deſire to have him for her Husband; but his Love was ſet on her younger; (I ſuppoſe it ſhould be) younger
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54462:16"/>Siſter, <hi>Ann,</hi> his preſent Wife; ſo rejected <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Solicitations: Which inraged her to that degree, that ever after her Anger was impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's before manifeſted under what Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances ſhe that's now his Wife was at the death of his firſt Wife, even ſo big with Child to him, that ſhe was delivered thereof about ſix Weeks after, and he married to her before that time of her delivery; how many Days or Weeks I know not; however, it's evident he was not a Widower above five or ſix Weeks, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps leſs; ſo that <hi>M. D.</hi> had a very ſhort time to ſolicite him, and ſeveral times to expreſs her great Affection and Deſire to have him for her Husband, as he faith: But looks as like a great Lye as may be; which will further appear by what follows.</p>
            <p>His firſt Wife I find to be buried the 24th of the third Month, commonly called <hi>May;</hi> and ſhe that's now his Wife was about that time greatly ſuſpected to be with Child by him; as well ſhe might, being then ſo far gone therewith; but, upon the 2d of the 4th Month, called <hi>June,</hi> next and immediately following, it was fully diſcovered and known, unto her Siſter <hi>Mary</hi> and Relations, to be with Child by the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> So that the time that can in any reſpect be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for ſuch Solicitations, is reduced within the Compaſs of about Nine Days. And that time under ſtrong ſuſpicion of her Siſters being with Child as aforeſaid, which in reaſon may be admitted as ſufficient to prevent ſuch Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if there had been inclination thereto;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54462:16"/>which I believe not: Much more would the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge of her Siſters being with Child, to the Man that baſely ſaith, ſhe ſeveral times expreſſed her great Affection and Deſire to have him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For no doubt, but the diſcovery of that Uncleanneſs, and that the ſaid <hi>H. W.</hi> had ſo baſely abuſed her Siſter, would adminiſter occaſion of being highly offended at him; all Circumſtances conſidered, he having a Wife of his own, and an honeſt one too for ought that ever I heard; though ſhe had the hard hap of having a very diſhoneſt Husband, if not worſe: Such an one as that ſhe that ſhould expreſs her Affection and Deſire as aforeſaid, conſidering all his Circumſtances, ſo cloſe upon the death of his Wife, her death ſo ſudden and ſurpriſing, her Siſter then big with Child by him, muſt needs be concluded Mad, or greatly Infatuated, and bereaved of common Senſe and Reaſon. Wherefore pray conſider what ſort of Man this <hi>H. W.</hi> is, this very noted Paſſage highly detects him to be very baſe, enough to give the Reader a clearer ſight of him and his whole Book: Wherefore, pray further conſider what kind of Readers muſt his Book have, that believes him, who ſo frequently detects himſelf of great Falſhood? I know none that believes him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his nameleſs as well as ſhameleſs Publiſher, who is like one of them who ſaid, <hi>Report, and we will report it;</hi> yet may queſtion whether he dare ſo far expreſs himſelf as to give us his Name, with his belief of the Truth of <hi>H. W</hi>'s Book, which he has publiſhed; eſpecially now when <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Book is expoſed, and his falſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54462:17"/>Covers plucked off, and he proving a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Man, as alſo very falſe and malicious. And I would hope, that ſuch as have abetted him, and put him upon Printing ſuch falſe, malicious, ſlanderous, as well as ſenſleſs Stuff, will now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thereof, with reſpect to their Repute and Credit; and to prevent what will be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of all that are acceſſory to ſuch an evil Work, <hi>viz. Shame and Confuſion of Face.</hi> And may it not be expected that he whom <hi>H. W.</hi> calls Excellent, Learned and Pious Mr. <hi>Gilpin,</hi> Miniſter then of their Church, and who the now Wife of <hi>H. W.</hi> confeſſed the 15th of the firſt Month now laſt paſt, 1696/7, before the four Friends before named, did write down all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters relating to <hi>H. W</hi>'s Narrative as they were tranſacted, will now ſee that he has been too officious on the behalf of ſuch a Man; and will ingenuouſly confeſs, that he was greatly miſtaken, or worſe, when on his behalf he gave that Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony related in Page 12 of the ſaid Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<q>That he <hi>H. W.</hi> was always accounted a very faithful and juſt Man; and that he had for a long time experienced him to be ſo.</q> Oh ſad! that a Man of his Figure and Station ſhould ſo miſtake, to ſpeak modeſtly, to give Teſtimony, and that, as he ſaith, <hi>upon long Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that he,</hi> viz. H. W. <hi>had always been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a very faithful and juſt Man;</hi> when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly known, as before related, to be both very unfaithful and unjuſt, at leaſt to his Wife: But Prejudice and Enmity has made many, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways wiſe, greatly to befool themſelves. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will <hi>J. N.</hi> whom he calls <hi>Deacon of their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54462:17"/>Church,</hi> get Repute either to himſelf or Church in Abetting or Teſtifying on behalf of <hi>H. W.</hi> if it be ſuch as he who is called Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> has Teſtified.</p>
            <p>Some few Paſſages more of the ſaid Book of <hi>H. W</hi>'s I ſhall take notice of, and ſo draw to a Concluſion with him, having exceeded what I intended; but that I find ſo much Dirt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move off the Innocent, and caſt back whence it came, and is worthy to ſtick.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, what I find related about the Search made on <hi>Sparkehead-Moore,</hi> in Page 9. Thus, <hi>They were ſlow, and had no great Courage to begin the Search; but my Wife ſpurred them on, and bid 'em chear up, and take Courage,</hi> &amp;c. Thus ſhe upbraided their Faintneſs and Folly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> She being examined about this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the four Friends before-named, the ſame 15th of the Firſt Month before-mentioned, 1697, She, <hi>viz. H. W</hi>'s Wife, anſwered, <hi>Yes, at the firſt I did put them on; but, I confeſs, my Spirit fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and I did cry out.</hi> It ſeems from this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that ſhe had neither Innocency nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence enough to ſupport her, but her Spirit fell and ſhe cried out: The Reaſon whereof I leave to God and her own Conſcience, in hope that her Heart is not yet grown ſo hard as her Husband's, ſince ſhe confeſſeth to ſome Truth.</p>
            <p>The next is, what I find in Page 16. <hi>viz. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Lord of his infinite free Mercy prel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my days with my dear and faithful Wife and Children, whom he hath increaſed, preſerved, and abundantly bleſſed: My whole Family he hath ſpared, as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54462:18"/>ſpares his own Son that ſerves him: And this I declare,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let ſuch as name the Holy Name of the Holy God, depart from Iniquity; for he will not be holden guiltleſs, <hi>that taketh his Name in vain;</hi> though he long ſpare, and his long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be very great; yet in the end, Tribulation and Anguiſh will be the Portion of the Wicked: Wherefore let <hi>H. W.</hi> hear and fear, and not bleſs himſelf in that he has been ſpared to this Day; nor boaſt of his Poſterity; for the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed has been ſeen ere now, to ſpread forth Branches like the green Bay Tree, and all things to go well with him, yet ſtands in a ſlippery place, ſuddenly goes down into the Pit; and Baſtard's Slips has not long nor deep Rooting; neither can Whoremongers, Adulterers, or Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, have any part or place in the Kingdom of Heaven; but in <hi>Tophet,</hi> prepared of old for the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            <p>In Page 21 he ſaith, <hi>I fell into a Temptation; wherein I was ſo caſt down, that I deſpaired to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Comfort any way, but in the Ordinances ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's evident he has not fallen into one only, but many Temptations and groſs Evils, which all his outward Ordinances cannot redeem him out of; for it's the Blood of Jeſus that cleanſeth from Sin, in which Remiſſion comes to be known in the Work of Regeneration and Renewings of the Holy Spirit, where there's unfeigned Repentance, and a walking in the Light: Which this Man reviles, and ſlights, and counts deceivable, and would falſly inſinuate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54462:18"/>to be the ground of his Erring from the way of Truth; which beſpeaks him in a dangerous Condition, blaſpheming againſt that Light in which all muſt walk, who comes to be cleanſed from all Sin; for if we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, we have Fellowſhip one with another, <hi>and the Blood of Jeſus his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. So that till <hi>H. W.</hi> turn to this Light, come to walk in it, even that which did not only manifeſt his Sin, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and condemned him therefore; and through the Convictions whereof he was made in time paſt (before he that led him into Sin had hardened his Heart) to confeſs his Sins and Tranſgreſſions, that he would now hide and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I ſay, till he come again to this Light, and incline to walk in it, all his outward Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances will never cleanſe him, nor make him a better Man, let him apply himſelf never ſo much thereto.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall now adviſe him, to look back at his Work, and conſider the Effects thereof, and ſee what Reproach he has brought upon himſelf, being fallen into the foul Pit of Infamy and Shame that he had digged for others; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to Criminate the Innocent <hi>Quakers,</hi> he has expoſed his own Crimes; would God that he and his Wife might yet ſee their ſad and diſmal Eſtate, and conſider whence they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and repent, and do their firſt Works, and ſo find a place of Repentance; if happily they have not ſo added Sin to Sin, and Rebellion to their great Wickedneſs knowingly; ſo as to provoke a merciful and long-ſuffering God, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54462:19"/>make them Examples of his Wrath and fiery In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; the eternal Portion of ſuch wicked and impenitent Sinners, which add Sin to Sin, till the Meaſure of their Iniquity be filled up; and it be ſaid, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing more is to be taken notice of, for the Information of the Reader; that is, part of his Title-Page, <hi>viz. Their malicious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of</hi> H. W. <hi>and his Wife as Murtherers, at the Publick Aſſize at</hi> Carliſle.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer; It's very fallaciouſly worded; ſo may deceive the unwary Reader, who may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from conclude, That there was ſome legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, that <hi>H. W.</hi> had been Called and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned at the Barr, had had a Trial, and the Iſſue of a Jury, and ſo an Aſſize Buſineſs; when, indeed, there was no ſuch thing; if there had, we ſhould have it to the full, or more. For in Page 6. <hi>They ſtretch things to the height:</hi> Which amounteth to thus much, That <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife was there, and the three Women alſo: That the Women drew up their Accuſations in Writing againſt <hi>H. W.</hi> and Wife, and caſt them in Towns and Streets (that muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came at <hi>Carliſle</hi>) at <hi>Carliſle</hi> gave one of their Papers to the judge; and he only bid them proceed according to Law, and they ſhould have Juſtice: That both Parties ſtaid all the time of the Aſſizes. And all elſe that the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did, was, that they bid <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife fear God. This is the Proſecution in full, as in the 6th Page before is by <hi>H. W.</hi> given: A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall Proſecution; if it may properly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:54462:19"/>
               <hi>One:</hi> The Woman gave the Judge one of their Papers, and bid <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife fear God. Who would have thought reading the Title-Page, as it is worded, but that their had been a formal Proſecution at the Aſſizes? And if the Man had meant honeſtly, we doubt not but he would have qualified the word <hi>Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> with Endeavours or Attempts of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: For all that was done by the ſaid three Women, at thoſe Aſſizes, can in t e greateſt ſtrictneſs amount to no more.</p>
            <p>Thus having taken notice of what I thought moſt material in his Book, which in any reſpect reflected upon Us, the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or the Holy Church which we make profeſſion of; wiping off the Dirt he throws at Us, turns it back upon himſelf, ſtripping off his deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Covers, and expoſeth him to the view of all to be a very unclean Man, an angry Apoſtate, demonſtrating wherein the <hi>three</hi> Women miſſed the way of Truth, and was diſowned therein: All which, as before inſerted, I now freely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and leave to the impartial and honeſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Cenſure and Judgment, and the Iſſue to the Lord: And ſhall now begin to ſay ſomething to the nameleſs Publiſher.</p>
            <p>But firſt, I ſhall note unto the Reader, That ſince I began the foregoing Anſwer to <hi>H. W.</hi> I am informed that there is already ſomething publiſhed in Print by another Hand, by way of Anſwer thereto, in a <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> to another name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Author; who, like this Publiſher, has vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54462:20"/>
            <p> Now to what the nameleſs Publiſher adds to the ſame Book, ſubſcribed by <hi>H. W.</hi> is ſuch a Piece, as I remember not that I have before read the like from any of our many envious Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers and malicious Detracters: Being ſuch a Piece of down right Railery, ſtuffed with Lyes, groſs Slanders, ungodly Perverſions, baſe inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations, and moſt ſordid and perverſe Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; yea, Blaſphemy and Contradictions, idle Stories, frothy and ſcurrilous Taunts, that to trace particularly in every thing would be a tedious Work, and more than I think need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, till he appear to own what he has charged, by giving us his Name; who, in the concealing of the ſame, may think himſelf ſecure; yet will render him and his Work very ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of great Injuſtice and Falſhood thereby; and ſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eakingly to charge that to wiſe, thinking, and judicious Readers, it might be ſufficient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Anſwer; yet, for the ſake of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary, and too credulous Readers, and for the better Information of ſuch as by this his Work, and the like, has entertained Prejudice againſt the Truth, and the Principle and Profeſſion thereof, as teſtified unto by the People common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and as a juſt Rebuke upon him, for his ungodly Work; I ſhall take notice of part thereof at preſent, not fearing his Roll of 13 Ells, or what elſe he mentions in his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> though it prove as bad, and as full of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, as what he has here expoſed againſt us.</p>
            <p>The Method I propoſe, for brevity ſake, is firſt to draw a Catalogue, Liſt, or Schedule, of ſome of his down-right Lyes and falſe Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb facs="tcp:54462:20"/>as I find them packed up thick and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold in his and <hi>H. W</hi>'s Book, and leave them at his Door as ſuch, with ſome ſhort Remarks ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned; challenging him, if he can or dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as a Man with his Name, to come forth to the Vindication or Proof thereof; till which, I look upon my ſelf, either on behalf of Truth, or the People I own and walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt, under no farther neceſſity of Anſwering: Which Catalogue, Liſt, or Schedule, take as followeth, under the Title of, <hi>Groſs Lyes and Slanders,</hi> of the nameleſs Publiſher of <hi>H. W</hi>'s Book.</p>
            <p>At his very Entrance, of what he adds in the <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> he begins with a Lye.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I find the</hi> Quakers <hi>in open Diſcord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Diſcord is betwixt the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> ſuch as <hi>H. W. &amp;c.</hi> and their Abettors: And we have Divine Authority, and Primitive Example, in denying ſuch Fellowſhip with us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Who cannot Err,</hi> &amp;c. Meaning the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We never ſaid ſo: But that all Men, as well as thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> are, as Men, lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to err, if they forſake the Conduct of that Eternal, Uunchangeable, Uunerring Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth, and is able to preſerve out of all Error; which theſe Men, our Oppoſers, ſlights and reviles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Curſed pretence to Divine Inſpiration, the ſtrongeſt Hold of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let him keep his curſed Pretence to himſelf; Divine Inſpiration we experience, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54462:21"/>Inſpiration of the Almighty, with the Effects thereof, bleſſed be God, according to Scripture: To call which, the ſtrongeſt Hold of the Devil, is not only a Lye, but Blaſphemy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Who knew</hi> all this <hi>Story</hi> 23 <hi>Years ago, and ſhould have diſclaimed the Actors, but did not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. All</hi> the Story of <hi>H. W</hi>'s, as in his Book, was never known before written, nor could be, becauſe many things therein inſerted were not true; being Stuff added to amuſe the Reader and abuſe the <hi>Quakers.</hi> It's evident, before that, what was to be diſclaimed was then done; and in Teſtimony thereof (tho' it diſcover his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Contradictions) he has made ſome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment in Page 24. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Some Friends, who at the firſt Aſſizes perſuaded the Women to do him Right, by Confeſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Next I ſhall repeat a whole heap of Lyes and Slanders; which, as he ſays, he takes out of what he calls, <hi>A further Eſſay, by a learned, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, compaſſionate Friend of ours;</hi> wherein he ſaith, <hi>He proves,</hi> &amp;c. But I ſay, Is not yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, nor can be.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>From their many Impertinences and Nonſence in their Books; which cannot, without Blaſphemy, be attributed to the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>From the many flat Contradictions of one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Pretender unto another, eſpecially their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Their ſcurrilous Railing at their beſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Their apparent Contradictions to plain Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54462:21"/> 9. <hi>Miſerable Perverſions, and groſs Miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Their Noval Opinions, not heard of before in the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>The allowed Novelty of their Sect; having no pretence to Succeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Their many Doctrines calculated to ſerve Popery, inſtanced in Nine Heads of Doctrine; wherein they agree with Papiſts againſt Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Notorious Poſſeſſions and Witchcrafts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Many groſs Blaſphemies uttered by thoſe ſo Inſpired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>VVallowing in groſs unnatural Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>VVild Attempts of long Faſting, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Contradiction to all other good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which before-ſaid, I take out of leſs than two Leaves of the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Book afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; enough, if there were no more, for this nameleſs Publiſher; and him he calls our <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Peaceable, Compaſſionate Friend;</hi> turning them all back, as groſs Lyes and impudent Slanders: For which he that ſits in Heaven, will rebuke them. And tho' the Publiſher have, <hi>Rabſhacah</hi> like, opened his Mouth wide againſt the Lord and his innocent People, yet I ſhall in the Name and on Behalf of that People tell him, his evil Deſign will be fruſtrated, and his Eyes grow dim, and Heart fail, before he can ever prove what he hath wrongfully charged. And I ſhall farther Anſwer them in the Words of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s God, through his Servant <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 37. Ver. 22, 23. <hi>viz. This is the word which the Lord
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54462:22"/>hath ſpoken concerning him, The Virgin, the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Zion, hath deſpiſed thee, and laughed thee to ſcorn, the Daughter of Jeruſalem hath ſhaken her head againſt thee. Whom haſt thou reproached and blaſphemed? And againſt whom haſt thou exalted thy Voice, and lifted up thine Eyes on high? Even againſt the Holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. In Page 23. <hi>A ſtrange Story this is, Reader, indeed, and beyond the Power, even of</hi> Quakers <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency, to deny; ſince it was ſo long tranſacting, ſo many Friends concerned in it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay it is the Publiſher's Impudency, to caſt upon the <hi>Quakers;</hi> and a great Lye, to ſay ſo many Friends were concerned it.</p>
            <p n="19">19. In Page 28. <hi>What think of you theſe dear Siſters? true</hi> Quakers <hi>they were, and owned as ſuch to the laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, It's not only a filthy Taunt, but a ſhameful Lye.</p>
            <p n="20">20. In Page 28. <hi>How many Chriſt's and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours will this People at length produce?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. In the ſame Page, mentioning the Terms and Way of his (meaning Chriſt's) ſaving, <hi>viz. They muſt value his Blood, and ſubmit to the Rule of his Word: But the</hi> Quakers, ſaith he, <hi>like not ſuch Terms; therefore will have a Second</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>Chriſt, or a Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. In ſame Page he ſaith, <hi>Now, ſhall we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, that</hi> Quakers <hi>offer us a new Creed, or Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſcorn our old Bible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. Again, in the ſame Page, <hi>When their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſays we muſt have a Second Saviour, a Carnal One too; and who is within none but a ſingle VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:54462:22"/> 24. Again, in the ſame Page, he ſaith, <hi>VVas a fit Brother for their Chriſt within,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="25">25. In the ſame 28th Page he ſaith, <hi>Is this all? No; we have more Chriſts among them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>See now, Reader, what heaps of Lyes this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure railing Man belcheth forth to his ſhame! And tho' he hide himſelf from Men, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing his Name, the Righteous God will find him out, to Reward him according to his Works. I deny them all, as impudent Lyes. But to proceed.</p>
            <p n="26">26. In Page 32 he ſaith, <hi>Then your Spirit, Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or</hi> Flatus, <hi>is your Supreme Rule,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, A horrid Lye and Slander! That Spirit which leads into all Truth, is that which we have always owned to be our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Rule; which, if he had been led by, would not have uttered ſo many Lyes and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; which manifeſts him to be of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Devil, who <hi>was a Lyer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. In Page 34 he faith, <hi>So</hi> G. F. <hi>had the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to receive Adoration and VVorſhip,</hi> &amp;c. Which, I ſay, is alſo another of his groſs Lyes upon the Dead.</p>
            <p n="28">28. In Page 35 he faith, <hi>VVill</hi> G. F. <hi>deny it? VVho declared himſelf equal with God, and received VVorſhip,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſay, It's alſo another impudent Lye caſt upon the Dead: Let him prove what he charges.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Again, in ſame Page he ſaith, <hi>As their</hi> (meaning the <hi>Quakers) Infallibility conſiſts with Lyes and Self-Contradiction; ſo can their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb facs="tcp:54462:23"/>ſtand with moſt abominable VVickedneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, His Slander herein is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Infallibility of the Eternal Spirit of Truth admits of no Lye nor Contradiction, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can abominable Wickedneſs ſtand with the Perfection that is the Product or Work of the Holy Ghoſt; or Spirit in all true Believers in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And we cannot but bear Teſtimony againſt abominable Wickedneſs, and all ſuch as wallow therein; as <hi>H. W.</hi> and other Apoſtates, which makes them and this their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Publiſher ſo grievous Angry, to load us with ſo many Calumnies.</p>
            <p n="30">30. In Page 37 he ſaith, That Jeſus deſcibed in Scripture was <hi>to ſeal up Viſion and Prophecy,</hi> Dan, 9.24. <hi>Or, to give ſuch perfect diſcovery of God's Counſel and Will to the World, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits extraordinary Gifts of Illumination ſhould be no more neceſſary, nor continued: But the</hi> Quakers, <hi>by pretending conſtant Prophetical Revelation from him</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>deny his Work aforeſaid, and that he has done his VVork; deny that he is come, or worſe; nay, that he ever was to come, or needs to come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What a Crotchet this Man has in his Head about the word <hi>Extraordinary!</hi> I know not, but that, <hi>That</hi> Jeſus deſcribed in Scripture was to <hi>ſeal up Viſion and Prophecy,</hi> or to give ſuch perfect Diſcovery of God's Counſel and Will to the World, by what is writeen in Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, That the Spirit's Gifts of Illumination ſhould be no more neceſſary nor continued, is denied, as Erroneous; and that of <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54462:23"/>inſtanced to prove the ſame, is no Proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the leaſt, without miſerable wreſting and miſconſtruing the ſame: A thing he falſly chargeth upon the <hi>Quakers;</hi> but declares his own Guilt therein. And there is great neceſſity for the continued Help and Illumination of the Holy Spirit; for without the Illumination thereof we can neither know God nor the things of God: For, as ſaith the Scripture, the things of God know no Man but by his Spirit; being that which ſearcheth into the revealeth the deep things of God; and is given of God, to lead into all Truth; whom the World cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him: <hi>But you know him, for he dwelleth with you, and ſhall be in you:</hi> Read <hi>John</hi> 14, 16, 17. And it's in and by the Illumination of this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that Chriſt revealeth himſelf unto his Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; and through which the true Believers in Chriſt are enabled to keep his Words: Such the Father loveth, and to ſuch the Father and Son cometh in this Eternal Spirit, and maketh their abode with: Read alſo Verſes 22, 23. And that the <hi>Quakers</hi> deny the Work of Chriſt; that he was to come, did come, or need to come; or, what is worſe; his falſe Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amounts to a four-fold Lye, and a great Slander: And to make his Slander greater (in what's worſe) let him tell what's worſe, if he can, than what he has before falſly charged: It ſeems his Mouth is full of bitter Stuff; and ſuch he vents without regard to Truth or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; being ſo drunken with Enmity, to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit out his own Shame and Filth; yet, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54462:24"/>looks upon himſelf ſafe in concealing his Name.</p>
            <p n="31">31. And further, in the Page laſt mentioned, he will needs be either a Reviler or Deceiver, in telling what the <hi>Quakers</hi> may be, <hi>viz. It's but,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to conſult their Light, it will give Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſe, like that</hi> cum fueris Romae, <hi>&amp;c. Then enter Father</hi> Molenos, <hi>all is done; they may in a new Senſe (as their Inward Chriſt will not fail to tell them) become all things to all Men, as already in Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits and Geſtures; ſo might be</hi> Papiſts <hi>and</hi> Turks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How this Man, who pretends great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to Scripture, and the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, Reflects upon both by his falſe and ungrounded Inferences! For, did not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles become all Things to all Men? Namely, for the gaining of ſome to the Truth; yet, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no occaſion became either <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Turks.</hi> Neither did the Apoſtles, nor Chriſt within (the Hope of Glory, without which all are Reprobates) ever give this Man's Reſponſe, who more and more expreſſeth himſelf to be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether regardleſs of Truth, Honeſty, or fair Dealing. But, to proceed.</p>
            <p n="32">32. In Page 38 he ſaith, <hi>One moſt fatally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicating Notion, I take to be that of the Saving Grace of God in all Men: What could Men deviſe more proud and provoking, to bring all God's Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Proviſions into Contempt? I can ſee nothing it ſaves, unleſs they mean, It ſaves them all Care and Pains in working out their Salvation; for no People ſleeps ſo ſecure as they, without all Fear or Spiritual Conflict.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54462:24"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such a Graceleſs as well as Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Aſperſion, as none but a graceleſs Man, or ſuch an one as has turned from Grace into Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs and great Enmity, having done deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, with his Name to it, will or dare to Aſſert; being ſo poſitive a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to Holy Scripture, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.12, 13. For the Grace of God, that bringeth Salvation, hath appeared to all Men, teaching Us (the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and Obeyers thereof) that denying all ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godlily, in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World. Is this Advice proud and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking, to bring all God's Remedial Proviſions to Contempt? Let him take heed whom he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes by ſuch Blaſphemies; the Text ſaying, <hi>It's the Grace of God that bringeth to Salvation:</hi> Then ſurely it's Saving, being God's Grace, by which the Saints were ſaved, through Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for they ſaid, <hi>by Grace we are ſaved:</hi> It taught them, as aforeſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Grace coming by Jeſus Chriſt, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of all that are ſaved, and appears within, as it is of God; becauſe that which may be known of God is manifeſt in them; for <hi>God hath ſhewed it unto them,</hi> Rom. 1.19. And who are taught, by this Grace that appeareth unto all Men, comes to Salvation; being God's Gift, through Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour; tho' too too many, to whom it appears and is Inwardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, doth Deſpite thereto, denies to be Taught thereby, turns it into Wantonneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thereby vain in their Imaginations, and their fooliſh Hearts come to be darkened,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54462:25"/>fruſtrating on their behalfs the Merciful end of God, on the account of the appearance of his Grace to them; the ſame that otherwiſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for their Salvation: So that Man's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is of himſelf; but Help and Salvation, only of the Lord; who gives the appearance of this Grace unto all Men, and Wills thereby the Salvation of all, not the Death of any Sinner, but rather that he ſhould come to be taught by this Grace, and be ſaved, and live. So that this Man manifeſts both his Pride and Provocation againſt God's Grace, and the Divine Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereto in the Holy Scripture, as well as ſlighting the Teaching thereof, and Ignorance of its bleſſed Work, in calling <hi>it, A fatally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicating Notion; proud and provoking, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. That he can ſee nothing it ſaves from, except, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It's not like he ſhould ſee or know what it ſaves from, who Blaſphemes againſt it; neither knows what Spiritual Conflicts they have who are taught by it; nor the ſufficiency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſupport through them all; as it was ſaid of God to be, to the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to wit, <hi>My Grace is ſufficient;</hi> being thereby ſtrengthened in the time of need. But, to proceed.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page, laſt mentioned, he goes on, and calls what before he called One moſt fatally intoxicating Notion; <hi>Now this one Anti-Scriptural Conceit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But how far he is wrong, and abuſive in this, and how agreeable the Teſtimony we bear on behalf of the Grace of God, is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent and agreeing with Divine Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I leave to the wiſe in Heart to judge. He
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54462:25"/>is reſolved to abuſe us, tho' it will at laſt turn upon himſelf with Shame.</p>
            <p n="33">33. He goes on in a frantick Fit of Railing; in which I confeſs him to be a very great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, excepting that his Heat runs him into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; but has made notable proviſion to keep himſelf hid, whatever he ſay, tho' never ſo Wicked and Falſe, by concealing his Name: he ſaith,
<q>No Guide ſo ſlippery as that they have choſen, a very <hi>Proteus,</hi> &amp;c. They can confeſs or deny Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh; they can own or diſown his Satisfaction and Righteouſneſs; value, or deride and decry his Benefits, Grace and Word, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> the Anti-Chriſt's in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Days were honeſt Men to you,</q> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Prov.</hi> 14.16. <hi>A wiſe Man feareth, and departeth from Evil; but the Fool ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and is confident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is it not he that decries and diſowns the Benefits of God? Doth not he ſay, He ſees nothing that it ſaves, and has not he choſen the ſlippery Guide, the very <hi>Proteus?</hi> The <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſaith he, can own or diſown, value or decry, his ſlippery Guide leads him into Confuſion and Self-Contradiction. For if they do value, as he ſaith they can do, then they cannot deride and decry Chriſt's Benefits, Grace and Word; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, for all his clamourous Noiſe againſt them; who would render them worſe than the Anti-Chriſt's in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time; nay, theſe Anti-Chriſts, honeſt Men, comparing as aforeſaid; yet fails in demonſtrating in what their Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty conſiſted. I conclude they had none; and, if he have any, none of it appears. And how
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54462:26"/>aptly that Text in <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.16. is applicable to him, ſober Reader judge.</p>
            <p>In Page the 40th I find another Piece full ſtuffed with Lyes, Slanders, and perfect Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Then is <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> contrary to the Doctrine that is of God? I know what Reſpect they give it, ſince a good Act of Parliament taught them what to ſay for <hi>Peace:</hi> But how elſe do they yet honour it? And, till they do, what ſort of Chriſtians can they be? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians, I find thoſe called, who received Chriſt's and his Apoſtles Doctrine, about the Perſon and Office of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p n="34">34. <q>But theſe (meaning the <hi>Quakers)</hi> do not they hereby confeſs another Chriſt? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, let the Reader obſerve this Man's Confuſion and Contradiction; for in Page 30 he ſaith, <hi>viz. We never knew, or ſhall know, what is the Doctrine of</hi> Quakeriſm: Yet in Page 40 affirms it to be <hi>contrary to the Doctrine that is of God.</hi> Can he or any Man elſe tell what that is, that he never knew nor ſhall know? But ſuch Stuff as is in an unclean Veſſel, muſt out when it opens; and the nauſeous ſmell thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares whence it comes. It's his great Abuſe of us to ſay, <hi>A good Act of Parliament taught us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We were taught, we bleſs the Lord, before that good Act, how to believe in, and what to ſay of the Doctrine of God and Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. But, no doubt, this obſcure Man is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Angry, that the Parliament ſhould Believe, or take Notice of our Sincere and Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54462:26"/>and Belief thereof; and vouchſafe unto us any Liberty, Peace, or Eaſe; ſince he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to Unchriſtian us, and inſinuate, that we do not yet honour the ſaid Doctrine, and at laſt ſay we do not in plain Words, as above. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inſinuating, we confeſs another Chriſt; which is falſe. And is not all this to expoſe us to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and the Wrath of Men? Yea, he far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſts his Deſign elſewhere: As Page 35. Thus, <hi>Againſt</hi> G. K. <hi>and Chriſt, without they'll bear Teſtimony; but none againſt the late King</hi> James <hi>and</hi> Popery. Again, in Page 39. Thus, <hi>But what's the matter that we ſo ſeldom hear of their Meſſages to Magiſtrates and Miniſters now adays? Why none to King</hi> William <hi>and his Parliament, as to</hi> Oliver <hi>and his?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mark the peaceable Mind and Innocency of unfighting unſwearing</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Had they not need to aſſure the Magiſtrates that now their Minds is changed? Elſe how unſure is the State and Church?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By which it's eaſie to gueſs what this Man would be at; <hi>New-England,</hi> Halters, or the like. <hi>But the curſt Cow has ſhort Horns,</hi> is the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb; and, bleſſed be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, we have great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in our Appeal to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as in former Times to all others; as with Reſpect to our Innocency and Peaceable Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour under every Government, that the Great God and Governor of all Things has ordered and permitted to be over us; ſo needs not change our Minds, having the Mind of our Lord Chriſt Jeſus, who has taught us neither to Fight nor to Swear; but to live Peaceably,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54462:27"/>and to put up our Prayers for Kings and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours; that we might live a Godly and Peaceable Life, in all Honeſty: And we have great Cauſe to bleſs God and be thankful, that we have, through his Aſſiſtance, been ſo preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in an Innocent and Peaceable Frame of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit towards the Governments, that the moſt wrathful of our Enemies or Detracters cannot juſtly charge the contrary. We have alſo cauſe of Thankfulneſs, That we are known to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to the preſent Government than this angry Man would repreſent us; and that we are vouchſafed Protection thereby, from what this and ſuch like reſtleſs Men would be at, whoſe Fingers itch to ſtir up Strife, Hatred, and Perſecution; which, if it be not the worſt part, is yet a very bad piece of Popery.</p>
            <p n="35">35. Again in Page 35 he ſaith, <hi>Adorn Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, which they profeſs not,</hi> (meaning the <hi>Quakers.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's another of his Lyes, a Shame to, and a Stain upon Chriſtian Doctrine and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, if he pretend or adviſe thereto; let him ſtop till he learn to ſpeak Truth, till he has got a Bridle to his Tongue, that unruly Member, that's ſet on fire; he may read by what; For, if the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi>'s Doctrine be true, and to be believed, we are not to take Notice of his ſeemign to be Religious, while he doth not Bridle his Tongue: Which, it's evident, this Man doth not. So concludes with the ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that this Man's Religion <hi>is but a vain pretence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:54462:27"/> 36. In Page 36 he ſaith, <hi>Beware of the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>Spirit and Inſinuation; it has often appeared, that ſuch as have adjoyned themſelves to them, are prepared for any Deluſions the Devil can ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A groſs Slander! The Divine Spirit which the <hi>Quakers</hi> Witneſs and bears Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to, delivers from and preſerves out of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions of the Devil; who it is that hath ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted this Lye againſt the Truth.</p>
            <p n="37">37. In Page 47. <hi>But theſe,</hi> ſaith he (meaning the <hi>Quakers) waxing ſecure and wanton in Formal Profeſſion, firſt caſt off all Ordinances, all Outward Duties, all Prayer, only with this Reſerve, when their own Spirits would give them a Jogg,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> His Charge is falſe and malicious, and beſpeaks him to be given up to ſerve the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lyes; as what he calls the <hi>Reſerve</hi> is idle and frothy. For it's by the Eternal Spirit that we are opened and aſſiſted in all our Duties to God, eſpecially Prayer; not knowing a right Underſtanding how to Pray, but by the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Help thereof; which made the Apoſtle conclude, he would Pray <hi>with the Spirit, and with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding:</hi> And ſo do we; and not a <hi>Jogg</hi> of our own Spirit, as he ſcoffingly ſaith.</p>
            <p n="38">38. In Page 48 He has another fling at Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>viz. Your Speakers,</hi> &amp;c. Alledging they know not who ſhall Speak, until the Spirit moves in that very Hour of the Aſſembly; nor what ſhall be ſpoken.
<q>A Conceit, ſays he (who has many idle ones in his Head) that has often made me ſmile, when I have been told a Week before-hand by your ſelves, That
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54462:28"/>ſuch a Man will, at ſuch a Day, ſpeak at ſuch Place.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Belike he dare not rely upon the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but muſt be ſtudying and taking Thought before-hand: Howbeit, I challenge him to name which of Us, and at what Time and Place, ſo told him, as aforeſaid: For I deny it, as a Lye (as he lays it down) invented by him, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Abuſe Us, and make way for a frothy Scoff.</p>
            <p n="39">39. In the ſame Page, <hi>viz. Since ſo many have</hi> (meaning the <hi>Quakers) undertaken to juſtifie that impudent Contradiction to the God of Order, and to baffle thoſe two plain Texts,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.34, 35. 1 Tim. 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny his Charge, as Impudent, calls on him for his Name and the Proof he is able to make, as for the two Texts before, and the Matter that relates thereto, I refer to a ſmall Treatiſe thereof, printed in the Year 1684, the 10th Month, Intituled, <hi>A Teſtimony to the fulfilling the Promiſe of God, relating to ſuch Women,</hi> &amp;c. Subſcribed by <hi>T. C.</hi> Alſo to <hi>R. B</hi>'s Appology; with ſeveral other of our Friends Books.</p>
            <p n="40">40. In Page 49 he ſaith,
<q>For God's Book has no Place nor Honour in your Aſſemblies; nor do your Teachers ſubmit themſelves or Doctrine to that Judge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by God's Book, he means the Holy Scriptures, I deny his Charge: For our Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as he calls them, whom we own, do Love and Honour Holy Scriptures; and ſubmit their Doctrine to be proved and tried thereby; as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54462:28"/>many Thouſands can Witneſs againſt this ſhameleſs Man.</p>
            <p>Thus having gone through his Work, I charge him with 40 moſt groſs Lyes and great Slanders; ſome of which are double, ſome tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, others fourfold, folded up one in another; which may perhaps double the Number; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what I have paſſed by and looked over, as of leſs moment, or in ſome degree related to what I have above taken Notice of; which I leave with him, as a Mark of Infamy upon him, till he appear like a Man, and quit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thereof; or elſe, repent of his Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein: and ſhall proceed to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſome of his Contradictions, and baſe Inferences, referring to other Things, and not before touched, relating to the <hi>South,</hi> to the Anſwer before-mentioned by <hi>B. C.</hi> And as to what he falſly alledgeth to be the Reaſon of <hi>H. W</hi>'s <hi>Converſion,</hi> as he calls it, I refer to what's before-ſaid to <hi>H. W</hi>'s Book; and ſhall only take ſome Notice of ſome of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="contradictions">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:54462:29"/>
            <head>Contradictions.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Title of the ſaid Book of <hi>H. W</hi>'s is, <hi>The Spirit of Quakeriſm,</hi> &amp;c. And again, towards the end of the <hi>Preface,</hi> thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Such as need to be further acquainted with the very Heart of <hi>Quakeriſm, compared with</hi> Page 31. <hi>viz.</hi> And thus it comes to paſs that we never know, nor ever ſhall know, what is the Doctrine of <hi>Quakeriſm.</hi>
               </q> I ſay, Can the Spirit and Heart of <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> be known, and yet not the Doctrine? Or, can he tell what that is he knoweth not?</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Page 39 he ſaith,
<q>The Scripture and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> are mutual Enemies.</q> What, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memies and yet Mutual! Oh ſtrange! What are they Mutual Enemies to the Devil and ſuch Lyars as he? Let him then conſider what he is an Enemy to. Yet, in Page 31.
<q>The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> we never know, nor ſhall know.</q> I ſay, Then how knows he, that the Scripture and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> are <hi>Mutual</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Again, Page 43. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>It was a juſt uſe of his Reaſon and Conſideration, guided by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that repreſented <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Compared with Page 31, aforeſaid;
<q>We never
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54462:29"/>know, nor ſhall know, what the Doctrine of <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> is.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In Page 23. he ſaith,
<q>The Devil himſelf (who one would think is ordinarily one of their Friends) ſeems here to have owed them a Spight.</q> For the Devil to be a Friend, and yet to owe us Spight, are contraries: We deny the Devil to be our Friend, let him take him, who is the Father of Lyes and Liars. This Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller grants the Devil has long owed us a Spight, and ſtill doth. Oh! how familiar he is with him! He knows his Mind! And that makes him thus to traduce us, and run into groſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Again, Page 24. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>I freely declare, if any of you ſincerely value Scripture Light, and Rule, and do not adhere to the guidance of this mad Spirit, this Story intends not to accuſe you.</q> Now, I ſay, if he holds here, he has cleared all the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general, except ſuch as are guided or adheres to be guided by a mad Spirit; and all ſuch the <hi>Quakers</hi> have and do deny to be of them: But that's not pleaſing to him to know or hear of. It's through their ſides that he would ſtrike at the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that are clear, and that he ſeems ſo freely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Story intends not to Accuſe; yet in the very next Page contradicts himſelf; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>What think you of the three dear Siſters? True <hi>Quakers</hi> they were, and owned as ſuch to the laſt: But what Spirit, what Wild-Fire is this, that they and you have choſen for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54462:30"/>your Guide?</q> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mark <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> they <hi>Quakers,</hi> here he writes in general, and makes no exception, as before: So that he's an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Body, will not hold to what he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But hear him again in the ſame Page, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>I will not be ſo <hi>Quaker</hi> like, as to cenſure a Multitude for ought, whereof I can find tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Proof that moſt are Innocent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To let paſs his Scoff of Quaker-like, it's evident through his whole Work, that he has ſencured Thouſands, a Multitude, that never heard hereof before: The which, one would have thought, might have been ſufficient Proof as to their Innocency, if he had been juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in what he ſays; and no doubt would, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, inaſmuch as he has no Proof; at leaſt, produceth none; that any owned the Three, whom he ſcoffingly calls, <hi>dear Siſters,</hi> in their endeavouring Proſecution of Law againſt <hi>H. W.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Only after ſeveral Eſſays and Onſets, amounts to mention one by Name, to wit, <hi>J. S.</hi> long ſince in his Grave; who, from the knowledge I had of him, and being charged only by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Perſons, that has moſt notoriouſly abuſed both dead and living, ſhall not believe it, till pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And if this one ſingle Perſon had been guilty, as charged, which I do not grant; yet who, beſides a Man nameleſs, or void of Shame, would on one Man's Fault Cenſure a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54462:30"/>And alſo thereby ſo far contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
            <p>Thus having taken Notice of his Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> Half a Dozen; I ſhall proceed to the idle Stories of <hi>P. Dalſton,</hi> and <hi>M. Mark,</hi> diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Perſons are pregnant Proofs, that the Man is Mad, Drunk, or greatly Intoxicated, with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Malice againſt the <hi>Quakers:</hi> eſpecially, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what baſe, frothy, ſordid and malicious Inferences, he draws from the Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe two Perſons, ſo overpowered by Melancholy, beſides their Reaſon, and diſtracted, to caſt upon the <hi>Quakers;</hi> yea, and rather than miſs, to beſpatter and calumniate the <hi>Quakers,</hi> he will make them act Rationally while they are Mad: But Wrath is cruel, and Anger is outragious; but who is able to ſtand before Envy?</p>
            <p>His like idle and ridiculous Story he gives of him whom he calls, <hi>An older and more crafty Friend; who by the like Revelation came to</hi> P. Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask him, what Revelation (his <hi>like</hi>) hath relation to the two mad diſtracted Perſons next before taken notice of? For it follows, <hi>the one of them,</hi> in his ſaid Book. Well then, will this Man ſay, That he that's led by the Revelation of a mad or diſtracted Man, can properly be called <hi>Crafty?</hi> What Craft appears in mad or diſtracted Men? For he ſaith before, That <hi>is was by Revelation, that</hi> P. Dalſon <hi>attempted to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Bed-Sheet, and was choaked in the trial.</hi> Was there any great Craft in that? And yet he ſaith, <hi>An older and more craftier Friend was he that
<pb facs="tcp:54462:31"/>came by the like Revelation.</hi> Then, methinks, he ſhould have the like Ends. This I have ſaid on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew the haſty Man his Contradiction and Folly. But, to ſay ſomething to his Story, I have heard of ſuch a Man as <hi>P. Hobſon;</hi> but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he was either reputed or went by the Name of a <hi>Quaker;</hi> neither doth this Publiſher give this crafty Friend of his, the Name of a <hi>Quaker;</hi> who rarely is ſhort in any Charge, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it may but affect the <hi>Quakers;</hi> wherefore, may be his Friend, or <hi>P. Hobſon</hi>'s. And as he is nameleſs, queſtioning whether there was ever either ſuch a Man or Thing as he relates, I ſhall leave it, as a Matter of his own forging; elſe, as a fit nameleſs Brother, to this nameleſs Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher.</p>
            <p>Next I ſhall take Notice of what he relates concerning <hi>W. Simpſon,</hi> one that I am not aſhamed to own to be one of Us; who, in the latter end of the time of <hi>O. Cromwell,</hi> had an Exerciſe upon his Spirit, to go through ſeveral Towns and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in this Nation, ſometimes naked, and with Aſhes upon his Head, and beſmeared, as a Sign to that Adulterous Generation of High Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, calling them to Repentance, and warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them of an approaching Judgment coming upon them who then had the Rule in both what was then called <hi>State and Church;</hi> for which he was often Impriſoned, Whipped, and evil Intreated, through the hardneſs of the Hearts of thoſe High Profeſſors then in Authority, and in their Pomp and Glory; which, in a little time after, was all laid in the Duſt, and they turned aſide, according to the Judgment fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54462:31"/>by <hi>W. S.</hi> which is worthy noticing. And what he adds about the Deſtruction of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> I deny, as falſe and forged, invented to aſperſe the Dead and calumniate the <hi>Quakers;</hi> againſt whom his Enmity is ſo great, that he cannot let them alone, though in their Graves.</p>
            <p>But proceeds to revile the People called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and the Truth that they profeſs and bear Teſtimony unto; eſpecially in that he ſo warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and zealouſly eſpouſeth the Cauſe of ſo vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unclean a Man, and old Apoſtate, as <hi>H. W.</hi> with other angry Apoſtates, as <hi>G. K.</hi> A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, ſomewhat reſembling that of the High-Prieſts with <hi>Judas:</hi> Wherefore take heed in time, leſt the Reward be like in the end.</p>
            <p>As to his like frivolous Stories, fetched from <hi>Briſtol, Somerſetſhire,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall refer the Reader to <hi>B. C</hi>'s Anſwer aforeſaid. And,</p>
            <p>To what he ſeems to vent his Spleen in, againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> in ſeveral Pages of his Book, I ſhall tell him that when he gives Us his Name, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to prove his Charge, falſly given againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> he may expect to have more: Till then, I tell him, it's below <hi>W. P.</hi> to take Notice of ſuch a nameleſs, ſculking, yet angry Scribler. And till then I ſhall leave him, and leave up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Mark and Character of one that vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and maliciouſly Smites at the Innocent in the Dark; hating the Light, becauſe his Deeds are Evil.</p>
            <p>Thus, Reader, having gone through <hi>H. W</hi>'s Book, and what his nameleſs Publiſher adds, and taken Notice of what I thought in any reſpect to be noticed, I ſhall (after due Peruſal, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54462:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>deliberate Conſideration, having regard to Truth and good Conſcience) leave thee, honeſt Reader, to judge thereof as thou ſhalt find occaſion; recommending thee to that which will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly give thee a right Underſtanding, as thou comes to be guided and directed thereby; <hi>to wit,</hi> the Holy Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth: and ſhall leave the Iſſue of this my Labour to the Lord; for whoſe Sake, his Truth and People, I have undertaken the ſame: As alſo to inform ſuch as may be ignorant of, or prejudiced againſt the Truth, through falſe and ſlanderous Reports caſt thereupon, through the Inſtigation of that old, wicked, reſtleſs, ſubtle E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to all Truth and Righteouſneſs. <hi>Out of whoſe Snares, that thou Reader, and all Men might be reſcued, and ſo preſerved, is the earneſt Prayer of him who is a well-wiſher to all Mankind,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Camſgil,</hi> 
                  <date>the 20th of the 3d Month, 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
